<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sir Ralph Hoptons and all his forces comming in to the Parliament. on Thursday last, according to the articles and propositions sent to him by Sir Thomas Fairfax, certified in two letters to the Honourable William Lenthall Esquire, Speaker of the Honourable house of Commons. Appointed by the Honourable William Lenthall Esquire Speaker of the Honorable House of Commons, to be forthwith printed and published.</title>
            <author>Rushworth, John, 1612?-1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92122</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2330</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E328_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200669</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861348</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861348</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159598</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92122)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159598)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 53:E328[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sir Ralph Hoptons and all his forces comming in to the Parliament. on Thursday last, according to the articles and propositions sent to him by Sir Thomas Fairfax, certified in two letters to the Honourable William Lenthall Esquire, Speaker of the Honourable house of Commons. Appointed by the Honourable William Lenthall Esquire Speaker of the Honorable House of Commons, to be forthwith printed and published.</title>
                  <author>Rushworth, John, 1612?-1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edward Husband, printer to the Honourable House of Commons.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>16. March 1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on A4r: J.R., i.e. John Rushworth.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: the second 6 in imprint date is crossed out and date altered to 1645.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hopton, Ralph Hopton, --  Baron, 1598-1652 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Campaigns --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159598:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 37 -->
            <p>SIR RALPH HOPTONS AND All his Forces comming in to the PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>On Thurſday laſt, according to the Articles and Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions ſent to him by <hi>SIR THOMAS FAIRFAX,</hi> Certified in two Letters to the Honourable <hi>William Lenthall</hi> Eſquire, Speaker of the Honourable houſe of Commons</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Appointed by the Honourable</hi> William Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thall <hi>Eſquire Speaker of the Honorable Houſe of Commons, to be forthwith printed and publiſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed for <hi>Edward Husband,</hi> Printer to the Honourable Houſe of Commons. 16. <hi>March</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:159598:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:159598:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
               <head>To the Honourable William Lenthall Eſquire, Speaker of the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſe of Commons.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N my laſt I acquainted you of the defeate given to a partie of the Enemies Horſe, wherein Major Generall <hi>Pert,</hi> and others were taken priſoners, being on Saterday laſt; And alſo of an inclination in the Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> to Treat, yet withall indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to get time, and a Ceſſation of Armes, both which were denied; Whereupon the Army advanced from their ſeverall Quarters; on Munday to <hi>Probus</hi> and <hi>Treguy,</hi> within foure or five miles of <hi>Truro;</hi> the head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quarter being at <hi>Treguy,</hi> where our forlorne came neere unto the Enemy; They ſtood in a peaceable manner, not offering to give reſiſtance, ſaying, There was a Ceſſation agreed unto, and they hoped there would bee a Peace; Our Officers had much adoe to perſwage them there was no Ceſſation, and therefore it did behove them not to ſtay any longer, but to retire to their places of advantage, or otherwiſe our Forces would (as they might at this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:159598:3"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->preſent have done) take advantage upon them, by falling on them; They did very kindly thanke our Officers and ſouldiers for their civilitie, that they did forbeare, there being no Ceſſation, and ſo retired backe. It is concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> did bruite this abroad amongſt his owne men, as concluded by us, to the intent that our men might fall foule on them, and ſo provoke them to ſome deſperate ingagement, but it had another effect, for the terrour was ſuch throughout their Army, upon the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of our whole Army in their ſight, that the Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> was inforced to ſend a Trumpet at twelve a clock at night to deſire a Parley, expreſſing his willingneſſe to loſe no time in making an end, and indeed if that had not come to keepe their men together, they had been in great diſorder: the offer was accepted; Whereupon about three a clock this morning the Trumpet was returned with our Commiſſioners names, <hi>viz.</hi> Commiſſary Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Jreton,</hi> Collonel <hi>Lambert,</hi> Commiſſary <hi>Stane,</hi> the Comptroller of the Ordnance, and Collonel <hi>S. Aubin,</hi> the place agreed to Treat at, was <hi>Treſilian</hi> Bridge neere <hi>Truro:</hi> The time nine aclock this morning, the Treaty to continue for three houres after, but the Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> fayled to ſend his Commiſſioners names till paſt nine: Our Army Horſe and Foot being at a Rendezvous by ſix aclock were advanced from their ſeverall Quarters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween nine and ten within two miles of <hi>Truro:</hi> The Trumpeter then comming with their Commiſſioners names, who are theſe, Collonel <hi>Goring,</hi> Collonel <hi>Pont,</hi> Collonel <hi>Bovel,</hi> Collonel <hi>Trever,</hi> and Sir <hi>Richard Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux,</hi> the Kings high Sheriffe of this County, whom they nominated to ballance the Kings high Sheriffe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated by the Parl. Col. S. <hi>Aubin:</hi> They deſired that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:159598:3"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->Collonel <hi>Goteere,</hi> a French man might be added, which was agreed unto, and Captaine <hi>Herle</hi> added to our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners: The ſafe Convoys from both Generals were ſent this day between ten and eleven of the clock, with a Letter further from the Generall, to the Lord <hi>Hopton,</hi> letting of him know, that his Army being upon a march, he intended to Quarter at <hi>Truro</hi> this night, which hee thought good to give him notice of, that his Forces may withdraw: And if he pleaſed, in regard it might be late before the Treaty could be agreed to; the bounds being ſet for each Army to quarter in, there might be a Ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Armes till to morrow morning at ſix of the clocke, by which time you need not doubt, but all things will be concluded on; the ſumme of the whole will bee as I conceive, and as Inſtructions are given, that accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Generalls firſt Propoſition, the Lord <hi>Hoptons</hi> Officers and Souldiers muſt all lay downe their Armes, yet the Officers to march away with their horſes and ſuch Armes they had wont to weare in peaceable times, and Paſſes to their ſeverall homes (or beyond Seas if they deſire it) ingaging themſelves never to beare Armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament, the common Souldiers to deliver up their Horſes and Armes, and to have allowed them twenty ſhillings a man to carry them home. By that Article I hope there will be good recruites, and numbers of horſes ſufficient got for the Armie. For the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigners and ſtrangers to have leave to depart the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, they likewiſe ingaging themſelves never to beare Armes more againſt the Parliament, the Officers to have their horſes with them. This indeed wee are informed will ſuit well with the ſtrangers deſires, they being afraid
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:159598:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->Quarter would bee denied them, as indeed moſt of them do deſerve it, but it is in relation to the point of time, That theſe things are propounded and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, to the end this field force might be totally ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered; That the Iriſh (which are ready, and are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day expected to land in theſe parts) may not have ſuch a Body of horſe to joyne with them.</p>
               <p>This is all the accompt I can give of this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, and I hope when it is effected (of which you need not doubt) the conſequence will be greater then is at preſent expected. God hath ſtrucke our enemies hearts with a feare, otherwiſe having ſuch a brave body of horſe they would not have beene com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to liſten to and ſeeke for a Treaty, within few houres there will another expreſſe bee ſent unto you, with the particulars of what is concluded, I thought good to diſpatch this Meſſenger away, (though the Journey be long) to prevent miſreports that might goe upon this buſſines.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>From the Rendevouz within 2. miles of <hi>Truro</hi> 
                     <date>March 10. 1645. 12. at noone.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your humble ſervant <hi>I. R.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:159598:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->
               <p>I Thought fit to ſtay the ſending of this Letter till next day and can give you this further accompt that the army according to former purpoſe marched into <hi>Truro</hi> and poſſeſt our ſelves of the Towne, and another part of it to St. <hi>Allens</hi> within leſſe then three miles of the North Sea (which is their only peece of Land the Enemy have left to break through, if they intend it) but our guards are ſo ſtrong, and our quarters ſo diſpoſed of, that there is not the leaſt feare of that. We have them now before us in a pound. The Commiſſioners met yeſterday about three of the clock continued Treating till almoſt tenne, ſome progreſſe they made, but there are ſo many circumſtances concerning the Articles and the manner of performing them as how theſe ſhalbe tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported &amp; goe beyond Sea<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> how theſe ſhalbe conveyed that are to goe to their ſeverall homes and other things of that nature, that it occaſioned a neceſſity laſt night to agree that the Treaty might continue for this day alſo, and their Commiſſioners to come this forenoone to <hi>Truro</hi> to finiſh the Treaty there, the Ceſſation being agreed too; their Souldiers come to our Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and wee goe to theirs, and they are now ſo fully poſſeſt of our fair intentions towards them, That it concernes the Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> to diſpatch the Treaty or elſe he is like to have few to attend him, The Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> doth really profeſſe he was igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the Princes going. That they are Traytors that had an hand in it, and I beleeve it is a thing that much workes with him, that the Prince ſhould be ſo carried away.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Truro</hi> 
                     <date>March 11. 11. at Noone.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>J. R.</hi> 15. <hi>Martii</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="update">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:159598:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 41 -->
               <p>THe 15. of <hi>March</hi> 1645. at foure of the clock in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon there came further intelligence by a Meſſenger from Sir <hi>Tho. Fairfax</hi> to the Honourable <hi>William Lenthall</hi> Eſquire, Speaker of the Honourable Houſe of Commons, certifying the comeing in of Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton</hi> with all his forces (being about two thouſand Horſe) to Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> according to the propoſitions within mentioned. Thurſday laſt being the day he and all his forces came in and ſubmitted. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſame intelligencer certifies, that on Wedneſday there came one hundred and twenty compleat armed Foot Souldiers to Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> out of <hi>Pendennis</hi> Caſtle, &amp; offer volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily to ſerve under his Excellency, and with him continue, and that the Prince is in the Iſle of <hi>Ceely.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:159598:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 42 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
